<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain queres modestly (though plainly) propounded to such as affect the congregational-way, and specially to Master Samuel Eaton and Mr. Timothy Taylor. With an epistle also directed to them concerning their late book intituled A defence of sundry positions, &amp;c. / By Richard Hollingworth, Mancuniensis.</title>
            <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E316_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158973</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86482)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158973)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 52:E316[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain queres modestly (though plainly) propounded to such as affect the congregational-way, and specially to Master Samuel Eaton and Mr. Timothy Taylor. With an epistle also directed to them concerning their late book intituled A defence of sundry positions, &amp;c. / By Richard Hollingworth, Mancuniensis.</title>
                  <author>Hollingworth, Richard, 1607-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ruth Raworth for Luke Fawn, and are to be sold at the singne of the Parrot in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 17. 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665. --  Defence of sundry positions and scriptures alleged to justifie the Congregationall-way.</term>
               <term>Taylor, Timothy, 1611 or 12-1681. --  Defence of sundry positions and scriptures alledged to justifie the Congregationall-way.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158973:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN QUERES Modeſtly (though plainly) Propounded to ſuch as affect the Congregational-way, And ſpecially To Maſter <hi>Samuel Eaton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Timothy Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH AN EPISTLE Alſo directed to them Concerning their late Book Intituled <hi>A Defence of ſundry Poſitions, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>Richard Hollinworth, Mancunienſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>You ſhall not turn aſide to the right hand, or to the left.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If they ſpeak not according to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſai. 8.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If the light that is in thee be darkneſſe, how great is that darkneſſe?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ruth Raworth</hi> for <hi>Luke Fawn,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Parrot in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:158973:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:158973:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have peruſed your <hi>defence</hi> lately Printed (which how able or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to juſtifie <hi>Independency,</hi> or to vindicate the <hi>Poſitions</hi> and <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> time may diſcover.) At pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent I have theſe few things to advertiſe you of.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you charge me with <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking you to be my Antagoniſts in Print</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In the Epiſtle.</note>; from which, I was ſo far, that when others (rather then my ſelf) thought fit the <hi>Examination of ſundry Scriptures, &amp;c.</hi> (which for the moſt part was an Anſwer to ſome <hi>Allegations,</hi> as they were privately made to me for ſatisfaction) ſhould be Printed, I gave ſpecial charge that neither my own name, nor the name of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:158973:3"/>much leſſe the name of other perſons and places ſhould be inſerted at length, in, or before the Book (though ſome few Copies came out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) leſt I ſhould ſeem either to provoke perſons, or reveal ſecrets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The deep and heavy charge</hi> (as you call it b) in the firſt part of my <hi>Preface</hi> againſt <hi>miſinterpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as a belying of God, counterfeiting the King of Kings hand, &amp;c.</hi> (Though I now ſee how I have ſped) I repent not of, nor ſee I cauſe why you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at it, or complain of it, if you have <hi>clearly manifeſted</hi> (as in your Title page you ſay you have) <hi>the Poſitions and Scriptures</hi> alleaged for your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and by me examined, <hi>to be ſufficient, pertinent, and full of power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I finde my ſelf deeply and heavily char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by you, <hi>To deprave places, to blot and blur ſweet humble ſpirited, holy pertinent expreſsions, to wrong the Elders of</hi> N. E. <hi>to wreſt allegations, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, though I ſaid, I will not tell you who ſaid <hi>All the Church is holy, ye take too much upon you:</hi> Yet you think it not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy my ſerious conſideration, Whether it might not be ſaid to me, as ſometimes Chriſt ſaid to one of the twelve, when he asked, Maſter <hi>Is it I,</hi> and he anſwered <hi>Thou haſt ſaid</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 85.15.</note>, (a bitter perſonal invective) What is your <hi>beloved brother,</hi> your <hi>good brother,</hi> as a <hi>Judas</hi> or <hi>Corah, Dathan, &amp;c?</hi> I hope in this (to ſay no more) we neither are, nor ſhall be Brethren, and deſire an humble modeſt Chriſtian Conteſtation with you, which are (in your own phraſe) <hi>my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſts in Print</hi> in this grave controverſie; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all calmly to conſider (what I ſpake in relation to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158973:3"/>your cauſe, not to any perſon) whether inveſting non-Elders with Miniſterial power, placing Church power in the body of the Congregation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the Elders that rule over them in the Lord, for taking too much upon them, be not the gain-ſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> a ſin of the new as well as of the old Teſtament? Whereof if I be guilty, I juſtly bear this reproach; if not, you have much wronged me; but God hath ſent you to do it, from whom I deſerve much worſe, though not from you any evil.</p>
            <p>The uſual occaſion of your cenſures of depraving places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a wide (I hope) not a willing miſtake in you, and not any iniquity in my hands or heart. You expect the Poſitions and Scriptures alleaged, to agree fully and exactly with the places cited in the Margent, which I neither profeſſed, nor intended, nor could effect without ſome (in mine opinion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting) alterations of them as they were alleaged to me. But on the contrary for evidence, that I followed another rule then the Printed Books (as at the firſt coming out of my Book, I advertiſed one of your Brethren) I ſometimes alleaged no Book at all, even where you know I might as <hi>Poſ.</hi> 4. Other times, that by comparing Arguments that otherwiſe came to hand with the Printed Books, I might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably intimate from whence they were taken, and alſo evidence the truth of what I ſaid in my <hi>Preface, That Independency for the moſt part produceth the ſame Texts in Print, which ſhe did in Preaching, Writing and Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> I alleaged Printed Books the <hi>By-ſtanders</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Preface</hi> with theſe or the like
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158973:4"/>clauſes,<note place="margin">See your own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, p. 1, 13, 14, 46, 78, 90.</note> 
               <hi>See almoſt the ſame Argument verbatim. The like you have. This though not ſo fully. This ſeems to be taken out of. Theſe Scriptures are alleaged though not with ſuch tartneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And ſometimes I alleaged for one Poſition (the ſecond for example) two or three Printed Books, differing poſſibly more then in phraſe one from another, which are ſo evident ſignes, that I tyed not my ſelf to the Printed Books, that I cannot but wonder that you did not obſerve it, which had you done, you needed not to have fought ſo earneſtly and frequently with your own fiction; for if it be acknowledged that the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alleaged witneſſe no ſuch thing as they are produced for,</hi> (whether they be in Printed Books or no) <hi>I</hi> (as I told you in my <hi>Preface</hi>) <hi>have my full end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have alſo either to bring an <hi>odium</hi> upon me, or the cauſe I plead, ſprinkled here and there, both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovingly and unneceſſarily ſome ſecret intimations of affecting Prelacy, whereas I in the worſt times was not ſo much, or no more Prelatical then the greateſt and godlieſt Independents in the Kingdom, if not at leaſt one of you have been (though what ever I was or am, that is no Anſwer to my Arguments) nor do I plead the cauſe of Prelacy which we have <hi>Covenanted to endeavour to the utmoſt to extirpate:</hi> But of the <hi>Government of the Reformed Churches which we have Covenanted to defend againſt the common enemy,</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by godly, learned men, our betters, known oppoſers of Prelacy, which have obtained a good report in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and the parts about it, <hi>viz.</hi> Maſter <hi>Burn</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Maſter <hi>Goſnol</hi> of <hi>Boulton,</hi> Maſter <hi>Fleetwood</hi> of <hi>Wigan,</hi> both Maſter <hi>Midſley's</hi> of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158973:4"/>
               <hi>Rachdal,</hi> Maſter <hi>Storer</hi> of <hi>Stockport,</hi> Maſter <hi>Hilderſham</hi> of <hi>Aſhby,</hi> Maſter <hi>Herring</hi> of <hi>Shrowesbury,</hi> Maſter <hi>Ball</hi> of <hi>Whitmore,</hi> Maſter <hi>John Paget</hi> (to omit his Brother Maſter <hi>Thomas Paget,</hi> and multitudes of others now alive) Maſter <hi>Hunt</hi> of <hi>Oldham,</hi> Maſter <hi>Rathband</hi> of <hi>Cockey,</hi> Maſter <hi>Gee</hi> of <hi>Newton,</hi> Maſter <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilecoat</hi> of <hi>Stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is the Presbyterian-way, a Prelatical-way, but a Social-way, as between Friends, Colleagues, Confederates, Brethren; where all judge, and all are judged, all things done <hi>communi conſilio;</hi> where no Congregation is above another Congregation, no Miniſter above another Miniſter; though the major part of them (as <hi>of the ſpirits of the Prophets to the prophets,</hi> and of Congregational Members, though equal one to another) be about the minor part; where every Elder is left to enjoy the Office of an Elder, and each Congregation left to the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Congregation, in what belongs to them, and they able to perform; where Presbyteries Claſſes, Synods of the ſame Congregations, or their Commiſſioners in matters of common concernment, do ſtrengthen and help particular Congregations, walking according to the rule, and reduce ſuch as walk not in truth and peace, but are leavened with errour and variance; and Elders upon a call, do teach, and rule, and perform all Miniſtrations with reference to, and the beſt advantage of the whole Church of Chriſt, though more ſpecially of thoſe parts of it, to which they are moſt related.</p>
            <p>Alſo, I cannot but obſerve, that there is a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between your Title-page, in which you ſay
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158973:5"/>indefinitely, That the <hi>Poſitions and Scriptures alleaged</hi> (not ſome or many of them) by me examined, <hi>are ſufficient, pertinent, and full of power,</hi> and are <hi>manifeſted,</hi> yea, <hi>clearly manifeſted</hi> ſo to be; and ſome other paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in your Book, in which you diſclaim the places applyed to <hi>Poſ.</hi> 23. as it is by me controverted, and are confident they are not found in the Works of any Congregational man.<note n="d" place="margin">P. 105.</note> And <hi>Poſ.</hi> 15. after the Allegation of ſome Authorities, in ſtead of anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Text (upon which, the diſtinction of <hi>Paſtors and Teachers</hi> is grounded) you the one, a <hi>Teacher,</hi> and the other <hi>Paſtor,</hi> conclude, <hi>If we do put a falſe gloſſe upon the Scripture, by miſ-interpreting of</hi> Epheſ. 4.11. <hi>yet more modeſt language</hi> (let any man finde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſtly in that examination, if he can) <hi>had become you brother, ſeeing ſuch Reverend and Learned men, whom your ſelf ſo much honour, have gone before us in this Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pag. 7. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note>. So <hi>Poſ.</hi> 19. do you <hi>clearly manifest,</hi> or ſo much as aſſert, that the Text <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. (what ever other Texts do) doth prove, That the Church muſt be Congregational. <hi>Poſ.</hi> 20. have you <hi>clearly manifeſted</hi> that <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. proves that the <hi>Keys were given to</hi> Peter <hi>to be uſed by him</hi> (for you could not but know that to be the meaning) as <hi>a Diſciple or Beleever, not as an Officer</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pa. 93. 1.</note>. <hi>Poſ.</hi> 12. have you clearly manifeſted that <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. proves the Churches power to cenſure her Officers, when the beſt Arguments you bring to prove <hi>Archippus</hi> his faultineſſe (without which it was no cenſure) amounts but to a <hi>ſtrong preſumption</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pa. 59. l. 14.</note>, and that you know is a weak proof, So <hi>Poſ.</hi> 2. have you <hi>clearly manifeſted</hi> from <hi>Adams</hi> family, <hi>that ſeven, eight or nine, make a Church,</hi> when for any thing you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158973:5"/>Anſwer, <hi>Adams</hi> family was no more a Church when they were ſeven or eight, then when they were but two or three, and do acknowledge (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your clear manifeſtation) that <hi>God hath not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely determined what number doth make a Church</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">P. 10. lin. 14, 33, 34.</note>. Alſo methinks you have not manifeſtly cleared, that <hi>Revel</hi> 8.8, 9. is <hi>ſufficient and full of power</hi> againſt ſettled endowments in the Church; of which Text you ſay <hi>Our brethren preſent their Expoſition, as probable; they force the Interpretation upon no man.</hi> And <hi>Poſ.</hi> 7. you do not manifeſtly clear that 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. doth pertinently and powerfully prove, that <hi>every Member at his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, doth promiſe to give himſelf</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">P. 68. l. 12.</note> 
               <hi>to the Church to be guided by them,</hi> when you ſay <hi>The practice of the Churches of</hi> Macedonia <hi>by way of alluſion</hi> is made uſe of; and the <hi>Argument is a comparatis:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">P 44. l. 18.</note> For you know Alluſions and Compariſons are not Argumentative. And <hi>Poſ.</hi> 13. inſtead of clear manifeſtation of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters maintenance out of the Stock of the Church, you ſay, <hi>We think</hi> we ſee moſt warrant for it from the New Teſtament; and <hi>as moſt probable once diſputed it;</hi> but neither then <hi>nor now are we peremptory</hi> in it<note n="l" place="margin">P. 61. l. 5, 6, 7.</note>. Finally, to omit more inſtances, when you ſay, <hi>We think, We conceive it is probable, &amp;c.</hi> or do never ſo confidently aſſert any of the ſeveral Poſitions, and do not prove the ſame by the ſeveral Texts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively alleaged, nor clear the ſaid Texts from all the Objections made againſt your Expoſition (one material Objection unanſwered, being enough to invalidate the ſame) you afford ſo many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to any wiſe Reader, that you have not clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſted the Poſitions and Scriptures (where
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158973:6"/>ſuch ſpeeches are found) to be ſufficient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for your pretending to prove ſome Poſitions and Practiſes by other Scriptures and Arguments (which makes your Book ſwell ſo big:) Suppoſe you ſhould really ſo prove them, yet that (as to mine intent expreſſed in the <hi>Preface</hi>) is but a <hi>by-matter;</hi> For Poſitions and Practiſes may be true and lawful, and yet not truely nor lawfully grounded on the Texts alleaged; and if I anſwer them, and you produce other new ones, we ſhall contend in <hi>infinitum,</hi> and not come to any iſſue. I could wiſh we might keep cloſe to the Scriptures and Poſitions alleaged, till they be one way or other cleared, and then we may more ſafely and orderly proceed to other Scriptures and Arguments.</p>
            <p>If the Poſitions and Scriptures be ſo clearly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, why do you not directly Anſwer the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, but obliquely and evadingly, in ſundry places? For inſtance, in the very firſt words of your firſt <hi>Reply,</hi> when I alleage one thing, <hi>viz. That the Apostles never taught or practiſied, to gather or ſeparate one part of this true Church, and another part of that (eſpecially perſons which themſelves converted not) to make a purer Church:</hi> You anſwer of another thing, which was never denyed. <hi>viz. The Apoſtles both taught and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed the ſeparating of ſome Jews from other Jews, and gathered them into a Chriſtian Church, while yet the Jewiſh Church</hi> (you ſay) <hi>was not diſſolved, but was a Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe you did ſolidly prove that the Church of the Jews was then a true Church: Yet firſt it was <hi>not a Chriſtian Church,</hi> nor are the <hi>Reformed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158973:6"/>Churches and Ministers</hi> to be compared to the then <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> thereof, and you ſhould prove Separation from a <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It was but one Church, and you ſhould ſhew gathering out of <hi>ſeveral</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It was onely of thoſe Jews which they <hi>converted to Christianity</hi> from <hi>unconverted Jews;</hi> and you ſhould ſhew the gathering of Chriſtians <hi>convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by others</hi> from other Chriſtians converted, as well as they, and (poſſibly) from thoſe perſons by whom they were converted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That Church was then by Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment to be diſſolved, and many Churches to be built upon its ruines; and therefore doth no more warrant the building of one Chriſtian Church upon the ruine of other true <hi>Chriſtian Churches,</hi> then the Parliaments Commiſſion (if there were ſuch a one) to the Inhabitants of <hi>Derby</hi> Hundred to take down <hi>Latham</hi> houſe to build them houſes of, doth warrant any one of the ſaid Inhabitants to take as many good ſtones as he can come by out of this, that, and the other Neighbours houſes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which they gave no ſuch commandment: Your not bringing a more punctual and pertinent proof, argues either an implicite confeſſion of the Truth of my Anſwer, or inability to oppugne it. A little after you diſcover too much willingneſſe to quarrel at my Expreſſions,<note place="margin">Pag. 6. l. 20, 25.</note> wherein you ſay <hi>I would ſuggeſt</hi> that you make Oppoſition to Magiſtracy. But doth not Maſter <hi>Weld</hi> a Congregational man, when Maſter <hi>Rathband</hi> chargeth Independents to hold that <hi>Christians may and ought to ſet up new
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158973:7"/>Churches, and practiſe in them all Gods Ordinances, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of a Chriſtian ſtate,</hi> yea, <hi>against their peremptory commands and eſtabliſhed Laws,</hi> and in the midſt, and againſt the minde of ſuch Churches as they freely acknowledge the true Churches of God, ſay of this Article, <hi>No Pen can expreſſe a greater latitude of Oppoſition againſt Magiſtracy,</hi> and Laws, and Churches too, then he affirms to be in us. Do not <hi>I uſe his own words? Print them in a different Character,</hi> cite him in the Margent? (which citation you (for what ends you know beſt) leave out as you do many others) ſhould you not blame Maſter <hi>Weld,</hi> or your ſelves, rather then me? This is but one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of many.</p>
            <p>And whereas according to rule and reaſon, he that affirms that ſuch a Scripture holds forth ſuch a Poſition, muſt prove it: You have a faculty, and make much uſe of it, when I ſhew you where the proof of the Poſition from the Text alleaged is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, and require you to ſupply that defect, to turn it over to me to prove the contrary: As 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. when I ſay the Churches of <hi>Galatia might for ought you alleage to the contrary, be combined one to another.</hi> The ſubſtance of your Anſwer to this paſſage is, <hi>Without proof we cannot grant them</hi> (<hi>id eſt,</hi> Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Churches) <hi>in Galatia:</hi> And (that you may more plauſibly put the buſineſſe off your ſelves) you leave out the words, <hi>For ought you alleage to the contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, becauſe charges of you for your indirect dealings without inſtances to make them good, are but weak; and Inſtances of the ſeveral kindes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158973:7"/>would too much enlarge this Epiſtle, I will now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them.</p>
            <p>And yet one thing being a great wrong to me, and to the Truth of God, I cannot paſſe by, <hi>viz.</hi> That you oftimes curtal and clip my Anſwers and Arguments, not onely the Supplement (which yet in a large Anſwer to a little Book in a Twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneths time, is ſcarce allowable) being in my cloſe ſtile very little; but alſo part of the ſubſtance and ſtrength of them, ſometimes folding them up in obſcure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where (you know) they cannot be read, ſometimes omitting them with a cenſure (as the ſeven particulars in <hi>Poſ.</hi> 24.) leſt the Reader (had you tranſcribed them) ſhould have expected an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſometimes not giving any hint or intimation of any thing omitted: For example, to omit the other places (for if they were all tranſcribed, they would augment this Epiſtle in ſundry pages, though my whole Examination (your Poſitions deducted) ſcarcely amounts to thirteen Leaves.) Out of my Examination of <hi>Poſ.</hi> 6. a main paſſage, <hi>viz. Gods Covenanting with</hi> Abraham, <hi>did not impoſe nor ſuppoſe an expreſſe vocal Covenant on</hi> Abrahams <hi>part, &amp;c.</hi> And out of my Examination of <hi>Poſ.</hi> 7. the principal part of my Anſwer, <hi>It is not ſaid that they gave themſelves to the Church or Churches, but to us,</hi> viz. <hi>Paul and Timothy, &amp;c.</hi> And out of my Examination, <hi>Poſ.</hi> 22. my whole Anſwer to <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.14. are by <hi>an Index Expurgatorius quite blotted out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Brethren, let me with love and meekneſſe reaſon with you; Do not you when you finde the <hi>ſhaddow of ſuch dealing</hi> in me, much complain of it? Is it not one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158973:8"/>errour under the Sun (and a great one too) in men, and perhaps in ſome good men, that they will ſtrive for victory rather then truth? Do not you omit that which you know to be pertinent, while you tranſcribe, and largely Anſwer ſome thing leſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent? You know many will read your Reply, that poſſibly will never ſee my Anſwer; and would you make them to beleeve that to thoſe Scriptures al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged in the Poſition, and publiſhed by my ſelf, I ſhould Anſwer either nothing at all, or no more, or otherwiſe then you ſet them down, that they may account me not onely weak (as I am) but ridiculous? Is this the fault of the Printer (who hath committed few other <hi>Errata</hi>'s, and left out I ſuppoſe none of your Reply) or is it your fault, who ſay in your Epiſtle, <hi>You think I will confeſſe your candor?</hi> Surely, Either the Printer or the Publiſher, have not delt kindly, nor candidly, but deceitfully with me, and the Reader. Cannot your cauſe or ſome particular of it, be maintained without ſuch dealing? Is this the way to <hi>clear manifeſtly the Poſitions and Scriptures to be ſufficient, pertinent, and full of power,</hi> by leaving out the Examination of them in whole or in part?</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſignified unto you <hi>ſome of thoſe plain things,</hi> which at the firſt reading of your Book ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preared, to me; and have alſo ſent you ſome <hi>Queres</hi> prepared, and ſhewed to ſome of your Brethren, and (poſſibly) to one, or both of you, before the coming out of your Reply, and little altered ſince, beſeeching you to hold out your way (as (you ſay) you are able) by giving not ſubtile onely, but ſolid Scriptural or Rational Anſwers to them all, as they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158973:8"/>reſpectively do require, and not to take and leave where you liſt, nor (ſeeing you know <hi>Quaeſtie quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem non ſelvit</hi>) to return Antiqueries (much leſſe cenſures) in ſtead of Anſwers, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if you ſhall do, I ſhall, if God thereunto aſſiſt, and his cauſe and the neceſſity of the Church do require, endeavour to Anſwer (when you have firſt anſwered theſe Queres) as alſo rejoyn to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (and that within the time Geometrically pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the time you took in Replying) with more mildeneſſe, clearneſſe, and candor, then you (as by this ſhort Epiſtle every wiſe Reader will eaſily ſee) have uſed in your Book.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The God of Truth, and Peace,<lb/> be with you, and your<lb/> loving Brother.<lb/> 
                  <hi>R. H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>November</hi> 29. 1645.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:158973:9"/>
            <head>Some <hi>Quere's</hi> mildely and modeſtly propounded to ſuch as affect the Congregational-way.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether to be <hi>wiſe, and holy, above or without the Rule,</hi> be not folly, prophaneneſſe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption?</p>
            <p>Are not unſcriptural wayes of procuring and preſerving Church-purity, as bad as <hi>voluntary humility and will-worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not <hi>humane inventions in Gods worſhip.</hi> impoſed by a Congregation upon her Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or freely obſerved by them, as oppoſite to the ſecond Commandment (at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in reſpect of the things themſelves) as if the Parliament or Aſſembly, had impoſed or ſhould impoſe or obſerve them?</p>
            <p>Are not ſuch <hi>humane inventions</hi> as are unjuſtly <hi>pretended to be Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> ſo much the more deteſtable to God and godly wiſe men, and more unlawful to be ſubmitted to, then if they were plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and practiſed as <hi>Inſtitutions of the Church?</hi> Was not Epiſcopacy the worſe when <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> was ſtamped on it?</p>
            <p>Whether profeſſion and practice of <hi>humane inventions,</hi> as <hi>a part of Gods Worſhip, or as eſſential</hi> to a Church, a Miniſter, or Church-Member, was not formerly eſteemed, and aſſerted to be; and is it not ſtill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian impiety, and much liker to procure Gods judgements on the Kingdom, then the diſcovery, confutation, and oppoſition of them?</p>
            <p>Whether they which in oppoſition to Presbyterial Government, the Government of the moſt, and beſt Reformed Churches, make Diſturbance, Diviſions, Separations, pretending their way is the <hi>Scriptural-way, the onely way,</hi> muſt not have as clear, yea, more clear
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158973:9"/>Scriptures for their way, then the other, or elſe be juſtly accounted enemies to Truth and Peace?</p>
            <p>Doth the Scripture require the <hi>new Conſtitution</hi> of any true Churches, (ſuch as the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> are confeſſed to be) and which already by your confeſſion, have the eſſence of Conſtitution, and where doth it require it?</p>
            <p>May not the ſaid Churches be fully reformed according to Gods Word without a <hi>new Conſtitution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth the Scripture uſe the phraſe <hi>gathering the Church,</hi> in the ſenſe that you uſe it, for the <hi>firſt Conſtitution</hi> or <hi>Coalition</hi> of a Church?</p>
            <p>By what name or names, is thè ſaid <hi>Church Conſtitution</hi> ſo much urged upon tender conſciences, called in Scripture?</p>
            <p>Did the Apoſtles or Miniſters in thoſe dayes teach or practiſe, to gather or ſeparate one part of this true Church (of the Jewiſh Church I ſpeak not, which was then by Gods Commandment to be diſſolved) and another part of that, yea, perſons which themſelves converted not to make out of them all a purer Church?</p>
            <p>Did they ſever the godly into bodies diſtinct from others of the ſame place, profeſſing the ſame Religion?</p>
            <p>Is it not the Scriptural-way of purging a corrupt Church, to caſt out the groſſeſt offenders firſt (as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in which were many <hi>Schiſmatikes, Heretikes, Fornicators, Drunken Communicants,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to <hi>caſt out the inceſtuous perſon</hi>) that others may hear and fear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo in caſe of Hereſie and Errour, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. and 6. Firſt, the Seducers were to be cut off; and they that <hi>were overtaken with a fault, to be reſtored with the ſpirit of meekneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not the ſetting up of a Church in a Church, and extracting the <hi>one</hi> out of the other, or out of Churches, imply the incorrigibleneſſe, incurableneſſe, diſſolving and diſanulling of that Church or Churches, out of which it is extracted?</p>
            <p>Doth meer Separation of Members from a confeſſed true Church, and Miniſtery endeavouring to reform according to her Light, without their admonition, aſſiſtance in the Work of Reformation, or ſo much as intimation to the Miniſters or Members, free their conſciences from the guilt of thoſe corruptions which they judge to be in that Church? Is it not a neglect of Chriſts rule, <hi>viz. Admonition, Tell him his fault, &amp;c.</hi> And the ſubſtitution of another in the place, <hi>viz. Separation,</hi> which is as it were an Excommunication of the Church. and beyond the Rule?</p>
            <p>Whether if ſeven, eight, nine, ten, twenty, ſeparating voluntati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yea, ſinfully (as if they turn <hi>Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Familiſts, Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians. Arminians</hi>) from a Congregation of an hundred, two hundred,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158973:10"/>or a thouſand, do by a particular Covenant combine themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are preſently thereupon exempt from the Juriſdiction of that Church, and have as much or more Church power, then they had while they were (as they ought ſtill to have been) Members of the ſaid Church, yea, do become a diſtinct Independent ſiſter Church?</p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Women</hi> (at leaſt Widows and Maids, that are <hi>ſui juris</hi>) be not engaged to-ſeek the participation of all Gods Ordinances; as well as men, and bound to joyn in Church-Covenant, whether any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of men, or any men at all do joyn with them or no?</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Paul</hi> converted thoſe Women to whom he preached; <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. which could not be brought into an Organical Congregation: can it be conceived that they (though Baptized) were ſtill <hi>without?</hi> were not their children <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>holy,</hi> having right to Baptiſm?</p>
            <p>If it be eſſential, that the Church ſhould be at firſt made up of <hi>viſible Saints;</hi> can a man in Faith joyn to any Church, or being joyned, bear Office, ſubmit to Cenſures, or give any Church reſpect unto her, at the Conſtitution whereof he was not preſent, nor knoweth the firſt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or poſſibly ſuſpecteth them to be unſound, ſeeing he may well doubt, whether <hi>the ſaid Church hath all the Eſſentials of a Church, or no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not that which was once Eſſential to a true Church ever Eſſential? and is not the matter of a Church, <hi>viſible Saints,</hi> as neceſſary in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation,</hi> as in the firſt <hi>conſtitution</hi> of it?</p>
            <p>Was every Member at his admiſſion into the Church in the Apoſtles times, called to give account of the Work of Grace in his heart? and how is that proved?</p>
            <p>Was the Congregation to judge, and what Congregation in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did ſo judge whether that work was wrought in his heart or no: and conſequently, whether he were to be admitted, or no?</p>
            <p>Did <hi>John Baptiſt:</hi> which <hi>Baptized Jeruſalem, and all Judel,</hi> yea, thoſe which he calls <hi>Generations of Vipers, Luke</hi> 3.7. with 21. and the Diſciples of Chriſt which <hi>Baptized more Diſciples then John,</hi> ſo much miſtake (though they were born and lived amongſt them) as to think every of them a true Saint of God? Was this groſſe miſtake the ground of their Baptizing ſo many of them? Did they prophane or proſtitute the Holy Virgin Ordinance of Baptiſm in baptizing ſo many thouſands, yea, myriads (for they could be no leſſe) amongſt whom were ſo few (very few comparatively,) either real or viſible Saints? Should they not have prepared the people better then thus, and letten them have walked ſometime in fellowſhip with them for approbation of their Converſation? for ſo the very Cells of Satan (ſay ſome) <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries</hi> and <hi>Nunneries,</hi> do before they admit any into their Society?</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:158973:10"/>
            <p> Was not the firſt (if not the onely) Church, founded by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>domeſtical</hi> in Chriſt's own Family (as the firſt Jewiſh Church was in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family,) in which, Chriſt himſelf, the Maſter of the houſe, who choſe the Apoſtles and not they him, was the Prieſt, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and Paſtour, (as alſo <hi>Adam, Noah, Abraham,</hi> in their Families) and in which, the Sacrament was adminiſtred and received (which we read not in other Families, called Churches;) and to which, Chriſt might have added many formerly converted by himſelf and others, and yet did not; and ſhould or may a family of twelve or thirteen be, and continue ſo long an entire Church, without adding one Member of any other family (though never ſo fit to be received) as Chriſts Family till it was diſſolved by his death did?</p>
            <p>Whether the Church being firſt <hi>Domeſtical</hi> and after <hi>Congregational,</hi> both the one, and the other, were not accidental to it (the Jewiſh Church having the eſſence of a Church when it was National, as well as while it was Congregational) and to the Office of an Apoſtle, then the onely Church Officer (ſeeing (themſelves ſay) an Officer and a Church, an Univerſal Officer and Univerſal Church, are Relatives) as it is accidental to a General to have but one Company or one Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>Whether Subordination of Eccleſiaſtical Judicatories, and the benefit of Appeals in the Old Teſtament, was meerly Ceremonial (though the High Prieſt, Temple, and ſome other things were) or was it grounded on natural Reaſon and Equity? and ſo far as it is ſo ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is it abrogated in the New Teſtament? and how doth the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it appear?</p>
            <p>Doth not 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. warrant an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal viſible Church, name,</hi> and <hi>thing,</hi> ſeeing it is improper to ſay That the Apoſtles which by Office had the care of all Churches, were ſet, put, or placed in any one? If they were Members of any particular Church, was it not rather of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> then of <hi>Corinth</hi> (to which, <hi>Paul</hi> did but come as to other Churches; and no other Apoſtle that we read of was there; and which at his Baptiſm was a meer <hi>non-ens;</hi> much leſſe were the <hi>Jews and Gentiles Baptized into the Corinthian Church</hi>)? Is not <hi>Paul's</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Ye are the Body of Chriſt,</hi> corrective of it ſelf: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Ye are not the whole Body,</hi> but <hi>members in part</hi> of that <hi>Body,</hi> in which, the Jewiſh and Gentiliſh Churches are ſaid to be <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 3.6. <hi>Whereof Paul was a Miniſter, Coloſ.</hi> 1.15. <hi>viz.</hi> The Catholike viſible Church?</p>
            <p>Is not this Body or Church Catholike <hi>totum integrale,</hi> and the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches <hi>ſimilares parte?</hi> Doth not the Scripture uſually ſet it down as <hi>one Spouſe, one Woman travelling, one Aſſembly of twenty four
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:158973:11"/>Elders, and four Beaſts, one City of God, one Houſhold, one Temple,</hi> (whereof the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> (being not the whole City, Houſhold, or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,) were <hi>fellow Citizens, of the Houſhold, and built together, viz.</hi> With other Churches and Children of God) <hi>one new Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> The Scripture not warranting the expreſſion of an hundred or a thouſand Cities of God, <hi>New Jeruſalem, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not the Scripture expreſſely, and almoſt in the fame words teach, That the Sacraments, Officers, and Cenſures, belong primarily to the Catholike viſible Church, when it ſaith, <hi>We are all Baptized into it, and in it God hath ſet not onely extraordinary perſons, callings, gifts, as Apoſtles, Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> but ordinary as <hi>Teachers</hi> (there is the ſame reaſon of <hi>Paſtors, Helps, Governments,</hi> in which the Cenſures are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded?</p>
            <p>If the Scripture allow the name and thing of an Univerſal viſible Church: If alſo the Jewiſh Chriſtian Churches be called in Scripture, <hi>one Bride, one new Jeruſalem,</hi> and all the Gentiles Churches <hi>one Siſter,</hi> and all the Jews and Gentiles converted <hi>one ſheep fold under one Shepherd;</hi> may not all the Churches in a Nation, living under one Civil Government, agreeing in one Confeſſion of Faith, and Directory for Worſhip, joyned in one Covenant, and repreſented ſometimes in one Aſſembly of themſelves, or their Meſſengers, be by warrant of Scripture called <hi>one Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether though National Churches were as lawful as either Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical or Congregational, There was in the Apoſtolike times any poſſibility of having a National Church when there was no Chriſtian Magiſtrate, (which we now eſteem a ſpecial bleſſing,) nor were Chriſtians ſo many as to bear the name of a Land or Nation (as if but one Family had been Chriſtian, the Church could not have been more then Domeſtical) nor had they liberty, ſafely and freely to meet in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synods or Aſſemblies (which yet we now hold lawful and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ordinances of God.) Could the Proteſtant Church be National in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> as it was in the days of King <hi>Edward,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether can a wiſe impartial man, which reads and conſiders the wonderful operations of the Sermons of <hi>John Baptiſt, Jeſus Chriſt, the twelve Apoſtles, and the ſeventy Diſciples,</hi> conceive that the one hundred and twenty, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. were the total number of the Chriſtians in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (among whom, were the eleven and the ſeventy) or the major part of them?</p>
            <p>Whether it be poſſible or probable, that all thoſe of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which were converted and Baptized before the death of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.1, 5, 6. <hi>John</hi> 4.12. and 12.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.17, 18. together with thoſe ſeveral
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158973:11"/>thouſands converted to Chriſtianity by <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> might not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their numbers, joyn in Publike Prayer, and Preaching, ſo that <hi>all might hear, and all might be edified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether doth any Scripture ſhew, that the many thouſands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> did meet ordinarily together to receive the Lords Supper (the chief Church Ordinance?) Can it be imagined, that ſo many at once could be accommodated with room, Beds to ſit, lye, or lean upon, (as Chriſt did according to the cuſtome of thoſe times) a Table to receive at, and Cups to drink in, eſpecially ſeeing that though they <hi>continued with one accord in the Temple, yet they brake Bread from houſe to houſe,</hi> (the Jews probably not permitting this new Ordinance in the Temple,) <hi>viz.</hi> In the ſeveral houſes of thoſe poor that then received the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>Can it be ſhewed that any Church in a City, or Town, how nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous ſoever it grew, was for the numeroſity of it, divided into two or more Churches (I ſpeak of Eccleſiaſtical Judicatories, not of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations) or that there were for that reaſon more Churches then one, in any one City or Town, and by what Scripture?</p>
            <p>Do not <hi>places</hi> in Scripture denominate Churches? Were not all the beleeving <hi>Corinthians</hi> of the <hi>Church of Corinth; the Brethren that were in Laodiced</hi> of the <hi>Church of Laodicea; the Saints in Epheſus; the Church of Epheſus, &amp;c?</hi> And each of them under the Juriſdiction reſpectively of <hi>Corinth, Laodicea,</hi> and <hi>Epheſus, &amp;c.?</hi> Is not this a patern uncontrolled by precepts and other paterns? Is there any example or warrant in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, That a Chriſtian living in a Town or City where there was a Church, was not, nor ought to be a member of that Church, but of a remoter Church?</p>
            <p>Did not Paſtors in Scripture <hi>feed the flock of God that was amongſt them?</hi> or can they watch over their flocks, or Church members one over an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as by Covenant they are bound, if they live five, ten, fifteen, twenty miles a ſunder?</p>
            <p>Can it be ſhewed that God in the Old or New Teſtament, did erect one Church without Officers? Seeing <hi>Adam</hi> was a Prieſt to his Wife and Family, and the firſt born afterwards were Prieſts at the founding of the Jewiſh Church, and Chriſt was an Officer to the Church in his houſe, and the Apoſtles were Officers in commiſſion at the founding of the Chriſtian Churches?</p>
            <p>Hath a Church without an Elder, or with one onely, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no <hi>Presbytery,</hi> power to cenſure, yea, excommunicate? Can an Inſtance be given of any ſuch incompleat Church that did exerciſe any Church Government? Or can it be proved by Scripture, that they might and ought to have exerciſed it?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:158973:12"/>
            <p> Doth not Election of, and Submiſſion to the ſame Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, ordinarily frequenting the ſame Ordinances and Worſhip, joynt maintenance of Officers and Ordinances (not to ſpeak how conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ohabitation and private Chriſtian Communion is) include a ſufficient, though an implicite covenant or conſent, which may be juſtified by holy Writ?</p>
            <p>Whether there be any Precept, direct or indirect, or Preſident at the founding of the firſt Churches, for a <hi>ſolemn expreſſe verbal Covenant or Agreement,</hi> more explicite then this? and if not, are not they guilty (to ſay no more) of ſtrange boldneſſe, which make it not onely lawful, but uſeful, and far better then the ſaid <hi>implicite Covenant,</hi> yea, a binding Ordinance of God, neceſſary, if not to the being, yet to the <hi>welbeing, ſtrength and purity of the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether there be a Church Covenant in Scripture (<hi>viz.</hi> which not onely in general promiſeth Service and Obedience. but hath alſo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial relation to <hi>Church State,</hi> and <hi>Church Members</hi> duties as ſuch, as marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Covenant hath to conjugal duties as ſuch?</p>
            <p>May not the Scripture Covenants, <hi>viz.</hi> God ſhall be our God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be taken by two or three, though too few to make a Church; or by one Family, or by perſons of ſeveral Churches, and yet leave them in the ſtate they were in, and not make them Members of a diſtinct Church, as <hi>Independents</hi> Covenants are ſaid to do?</p>
            <p>Whether Subſcription to your Confeſſion of Faith, be as eſſentially neceſſary to Church Conſtitution, as entering into Covenant? Is your Confeſſion the very ſame with the Confeſſions of other <hi>Independent Churches,</hi> or a Different? Is the Confeſſion of your later Churches, the very ſame with the Confeſſion of your former Churches? Do your ſelves eſteem all things therein unqueſtionable Fundamental Articles of Faith, ſeeing you require Subſcription to them all alike, as a Confeſſion of Faith, and that upon pain of Non-Admiſſion?</p>
            <p>Whether there be any Precept or Preſident in Scripture for requiring a Promiſe, before we admit Members, that they will not depart without the Churches leave? Is this a ſtanding Ordinance, or but a Politique invention, requiſite for the good of Societies ſo moulded? Are not Church Members Liberties much infringed, when they can neither diſpoſe of themſelves, or their children in Service, Marriage, and Factorſhip, remote from that Church, without diſcovering the cauſes them thereunto moving, (which is not alway fit and ſafe to be done,) and having Approbation and Diſmiſſion from her, which ſometimes is hard to be got, eſpecially for rich and uſeful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?</p>
            <p>Whether any Apoſtle or other in the Primitive times, did refuſe to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158973:12"/>admit any known beloever to the Sacrament, becauſe he was not (to uſe the new phraſe of theſe times) in <hi>Church-ſtate,</hi> or that they enquired of him whether he was convenanted into ſome particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that ſuch a one as they might lawfully hold Communion with?</p>
            <p>Was the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and of the Diſciples, and Apoſtles of Chriſt, a Seal of Congregation Communion? Was <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, and the Ennuch, Baptized into a particular Congregation? did not the ordinary Paſtors of <hi>Corinth</hi> Adminiſter that <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi> ahd Baptize in the ſame Body that <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did, and that <hi>Paul Baptized Criſpus and Gains, and the houſhould of Stephanas</hi> into? Is Baptiſm one time a Seal principally of Congregational Communion, and other times not? and what Scripture is there to warrant ſuch a diſtinction?</p>
            <p>Whether every Congregation which joyns in Covenant, doth, or muſt conſiſt of all, or ſome Chriſtians able to try the ſufficiency of an Elder, yea, fit to diſcharge that Office? Or, whether viſible Sanctiry without ſuch ability, be not ſufficient? And may this Congregation lawfully, (without aſſiſtance of others, unleſſe themſelves pleaſe,) notwithſtanding their apparent inability, chuſe their own Miniſter, and that one of themſelves alſo which muſt needs be an Inſufficient one?</p>
            <p>May this Congregation alſo (ſuppoſe they had a godly learned Paſtor) proceed againſt him in caſe of Errour and Hereſie, even to Depoſition and Excommunication. if their weakneſſe ſhall judge it fit? And is the ſaid Depoſition valid (whether juſt and unjuſt) unleſſe the ſaid Church be pleaſed to recal it, to deprive the ſaid Paſtor of his Miniſterial Authority and Office; and is there no remedy in ſuch a caſe?</p>
            <p>Is it not improper to call them that <hi>rule onely,</hi> by the name of <hi>Elders;</hi> and them that both rule and labour in the Word and Doctrine, by a meaner name, <hi>Miniſters?</hi> Doth the Scripture apply the name of Elders, rather to Ruling then to Preaching Elders; and if it doth not, why ſhould we?</p>
            <p>Are the Miniſters in the New Teſtament called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>The Miniſters or Deacons of the Church, or of the people?</hi> Are they not uſually called <hi>Miniſters of the Lord, of God, of Chriſt, of the New Teſtament, of the Goſpel, of the Word, &amp;c?</hi> and with reference to their people, <hi>Elders, Rulers. Paſtors, Teachers, Overſeers, Miniſters for them, &amp;c?</hi> Doth that Expreſſion in the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Chap. 4. Verſ. 5. <hi>Our ſelves your ſervants</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Paul</hi> call-himſelf as well as others; <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> imply, that he received his <hi>Authority and Office from the Church,</hi> did Officiate in their names,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:158973:13"/>
               <hi>was cenſurable by them, as a ſervant by his Maſter;</hi> or that he made himſelf a ſervant to them, as Chriſt did to his Diſciples, and as all good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters do to their Flocks for their good?</p>
            <p>Are the <hi>ſpirits of the Prophets ſubject to the people, or to the Prophets?</hi> Is not this ſubjection of the Spirits of the Prophets, to the Prophets, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the fewer to the greater number, as well in Synods and Aſſemblies of Churches, or of their Meſſengers, as in particular Congregations?</p>
            <p>Whether theſe two Propoſitions <hi>[Synods or Aſſemblies of Churches, or of their Meſſengers</hi> (to ſay nothing now of their Juriſdiction) <hi>are Gods Ordinances,</hi>] and [<hi>Every particular Congregation may, yea, muſt enjoy all Gods Ordinances within it ſelf]</hi> be not croſſe and contrary one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or how are they reconciled according to Scripture grounds?</p>
            <p>Is it any priviledge for Congrogations to ſubſiſt every one by her ſelf? May they not ſtand and flouriſh ſurer and better in an holy and Brotherly combination, and coordinate ſubjection, then in a divided ſingularity?</p>
            <p>Doth not Communion of particular Churches require, and the light of nature, and the equity of Scripture rules, and examples teach, that they may, and ought to enter into mutual Conſociation or Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt themſelves, in Claſſes and Synods, that they may ſo far as conveniently can be, make uſe of common conſent and mutual aſſiſtance, eſpecially in thoſe things that are of greater moment?</p>
            <p>If the Keyes be given to Beleevers to be exerciſed by them as Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, then are they not given to all beleevers: whether in Church Covenant or no, Church Members or no? If they be given to Church Members as ſuch, doth it not then follow, that <hi>Paſtors</hi> as <hi>Paſors,</hi> or <hi>Elders</hi> as <hi>Elders,</hi> have no more power of the Keyes then othher Church Members? And may not women as Church Members challenge power and right in them, do they not challenge the ſame in ſome of the new Congregations?</p>
            <p>Is not inveſting Non-Elders with Miniſterial power, placing the power of the Keys in the Body of the Congregation, and complaining of the Elders that rule well, for taking too much upon them, the ſin of <hi>Corah?</hi> Is it not a ſin of the New, as well as of the Old Teſtament? Doth <hi>Jude</hi> Hiſtorically or Prophetically ſpeak of it? If Prophetically? When, and in whom is it, or ſhall be fulfilled?</p>
            <p>Doth Election without Ordination make the Officer? Were the ſeven choſen by the people, <hi>Acts 6.</hi> Officers by vertue of their Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, before the Apoſtles prayed and impoſed hands? If ſo, then did not the <hi>people</hi> rather then <hi>the Apoſtles appoint them over the buſineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Ordination be leſſe then Election, then why is <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> rather then lifting up of hands in ſuffrages, reckoned amongſt the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158973:13"/>
               <hi>Principles, Heb 6.</hi> Why is the charge more expreſſe that Ordination (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Election) ſhould not be <hi>ſuddenly</hi> and <hi>haſtily made?</hi> Why is the deſcription of perſons to be ordained much more large in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> which were to ordain, then of perſons to be elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any or all the Epiſtles written to the Churches to whom ſuch election is conceived to belong?</p>
            <p>Is Ordination of Miniſters an act of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> power, or of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberty?</p>
            <p>Did the Apoſtles (which you confeſſe<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren</note> did wherever they came, leave the Elders and people to the exerciſe of that right which be longed to them) inveſt non-Elders with the power of Ordaining?</p>
            <p>Did not Churches wait, and not ordain their own Elders? (though they had as much Authority, and knew it as well as Churches now do) Did not the Apoſtles go themſelves to <hi>ordain Elders in every Church,</hi> or ſend ſome Elders or other to that purpoſe?</p>
            <p>Doth the Scripture require that every particular Congregation <hi>may,</hi> yea <hi>muſt</hi> (though ſhe hath neighbour-Congregations to aſſiſt which is our caſe) alone ordain her own Elders?</p>
            <p>What one Elder in Scripture was ordained by thoſe that were onely of that particular Congregation where he was to officiate?</p>
            <p>What may be the reaſon that the Apoſtle (which did all things fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) writing to ſo many Churches (in each of which was a particular Elderſhip) did not ſo largely (if at all) ſet down Rules for Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did the Presbytery that ordained <hi>Timothy,</hi> conſiſt onely of one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation? and of what Congregation? and how is it proved?</p>
            <p>Was not every Apoſtle (as alſo <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>) as it were an Elderſhip of the Churches extraordinarily combined in one man?</p>
            <p>When the Apoſtles joyned with other <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lders in Ordination, under what notion did they joyn? as <hi>Elders of ſundry Churches,</hi> or onely as Co-elders of that particular Congregation? If under the later noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what did they adde unto them; the Elders of a Church, being but Three or Four, having as much power as if by addition of Two or Three they were made Five or Six?</p>
            <p>May we not grant in ſome caſes that <hi>Supreme Civil</hi> power (ſuppoſe in executing one that had murderer his father and attempted to murder his mother) as well as <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> may be exerciſed in <hi>one Congregation,</hi> yea, in <hi>one family</hi> (if it be in a wilderneſſe, when it can have no aſſiſtance in Government) without having the leaſt thought that in ordinary eaſes every Congregation or Family ought to be Independent in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical or Civil matters?</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:158973:14"/>
            <p> Ordinary Elders impoſing hands on Apoſtles or Apoſtolike men, as you ſay the Teachers of <hi>Anttoch ordained Paul an Apoſtle, Act.</hi> 13.1, 2, did they ſet him apart to officiate onely <hi>in one,</hi> their own Congregation, and not in other Churches? For example, not in <hi>Rome,</hi> to which <hi>Paul</hi> writing, calls himſelf, with reference to that Ordination. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>an Apoſtle ſeparated,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Is there not as many precepts or preſidents for admitting to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament known Chriſtians of no ſet Congregation (which you ſo much boggle at) as of admitting the members of other Churches and their children, which you commonly practice?</p>
            <p>Do not Elders receive their power and commiſſion for the whole Church of Chriſt, and may they not (having a Call) preach in any Congregation, adminiſter the Sacrament to any Chriſtian, yea, vote in any Synod, as the Scotiſh Divines by conſent do vote in our Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly?</p>
            <p>Doth not communion of Churches bring communion of Offices and Officers? Elſe how can a Miniſter adminiſter the Sacrament as an Officer (for as a gifted man, he cannot diſpenſe it) to men of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, by vertue of the ſaid communion of Churches? And if ſo, why may not an Elder of other Churches in Juriſdiction?</p>
            <p>If recommendation be as it were a diſmiſſion (by your own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) differing not really, but onely in time; may not a Miniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended, that is, diſmiſſed for a time, act Miniſterially in another Congregation? may not the Maior of one Corporation, by conſent of all parties intereſted, act authoritatively out of the ſaid Corporation? (as the Maior of <hi>London</hi> is Bayliff of <hi>Southwark</hi>) And may not the Colonels of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> (your own ſimilitudes) by like conſent govern and rule the Souldiery of <hi>Cheſhire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is not the whole Church of God one Corporation, one City <hi>(ut ſupra)?</hi> —And may not then the Aldermen and Officers, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their ſeveral Wards, Limits, Companies, joyn together in a Court of Common counſel for the Government of the City?</p>
            <p>May a Paſtor, as a Paſtor, pray for the Univerſal Church, or no?</p>
            <p>Is it a divine or but an humane Inſtitution, that Miniſters ſhould be maintained by Lords-day collections? If humane; can any man which holds all Humane Inſtitutions unlawful, with good conſcience offer at thoſe Collections? If you ſay it is divine; where is the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it? Dare you determine it as certain, or do you but diſpute it as probable?</p>
            <p>Do not thoſe Independent Miniſters which enjoy Church lands, and receive Tythes or compoſitions for them, or yeerly, half yeerly, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158973:14"/>ſtipends, hold theſe ways of maintenance as lawful as Lords-day-collection?</p>
            <p>By what Scripture prove ye that it is the duty of any Chriſtians that are not of your Church (nor ever were) but are by you excluded out of it (poſſibly becauſe they will not take your Covenant, or ſubſcribe your Confeſſion, or the like) to contribute to your maintenance; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you take no charge of them, nor ſo much as preach to them as Paſtors? Have you from Chriſt any power to receive maintenance from ſuch?</p>
            <p>May a Church, to ſave charges, make it a rule or conſtant practice to chuſe no Ruling-elders, though never ſo fit and able, but ſuch as are able to maintain themſelves? Doth not that Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, hold forth the maintenance (notwithſtanding the poverty of thoſe times) as well as the lawfulneſſe of Ruling elders?</p>
            <p>Whether Moderators and Preſidents of Synods and Church-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, Aſſeſſors, Scribes, and Regiſters of Church-proceedings (to ſay nothing of ringing Bells to publike Worſhip) be lawful and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or no? Are theſe Offices grounded on Scripture, or on Reaſon, or the light of Nature?</p>
            <p>Hath God any where forbidden that he that exerciſeth thoſe Offices of Preſidency or Moderatorſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in one Synod, ſhould exerciſe them in the next, and in the third, fourth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> while he is willing able, faithful in diſcharge of his duty, and is thereunto elected and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved?</p>
            <p>Is not the preaching of the Word the higheſt and hardeſt part of the Miniſterial Function, in reſpect of which. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things!</hi> And if ſo; by what warrant do private men unfit for the meaneſt Office in the Miniſtery, ſo ordinarily and preſumptuouſly uſurp it, and yet are juſtified by ſome of you?</p>
            <p>How dare non-Elders, which have no commiſſion from Chriſt to Preach and Baptize, nor power to receive maintenance, uſually and publikely preach the Word in the Congregations, and receive mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the ſame? Do not they themſelves ſin, and all they which uſually hear and maintain them in their way; eſpecially ſuch as may hear true Miniſters as able and as faithful men as they?</p>
            <p>Hath not any in the Congregation (by their own grounds) as much authority to preach and receive maintenance, if the Congregation judge him gifted, and deſire it?</p>
            <p>Doth the abſence or diſſent of ſome or of the minor part of the Congregation diſannul the election of an Officer, admiſſion, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> of a member, or other Church-proceedings? or is the minor part bound to reſt in the vote of the major part, though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158973:15"/>contrary to their own judgements? or muſt they ſeparate from the Church, in caſe they conceive the major part doth ſin in ſuch election, admiſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> leſt they be leavened?</p>
            <p>Are not all bound in conſcience ordinarily to hear their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which themſelves, or their husbands, or parents, or the major part of the religious in their Congregation did either elect or afterward conſent and freely ſubmit to? (which after conſent, in the caſe of <hi>Leah,</hi> was enough to make a Marriage) Or is every Chriſtian notwithſtanding this, at liberty to hear whomſoever and whenſoever they pleaſe, even upon Sabbath days, when they conceive he is bound to preach?</p>
            <p>Were not husbands, wives and children alway of one and the ſame Church? Doth the vote of the husband, or his joyning to this or that true Church, include the vote and joyning of his wife and children un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Government? Is it not then a diſorderly unſcriptural practice that husbands ſhould be of one true Church, and wives (and that often without their husbands privity) of another, and children poſſibly of a third? Can an example of the like be ſhewed?</p>
            <p>Can Maſters of Families (in ſuch a caſe) take that care that thoſe that are under their Government do ſanctifie the Sabbath, which by the moral Law of God they are obliged to take, when one go's one way, another a ſecond, another a third?</p>
            <p>Whether there be any precept or preſident in Scripture for ſuſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any member of a particular Church or Congregation from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, who is not at the ſame time caſt out of the Church? and where is it?</p>
            <p>Whether any greater degree of knowledge and ſanctity ought to be required from any before we admit them to the Sacrament, then Chriſt required of all thoſe which he admitted to it; if ſo great a degree may be required, conſidering what men they were, and what means they enjoyed?</p>
            <p>Doth the Scripture contain in it any precept, preſident or warrant that a man ſhould refuſe to communicate where either the Presbytery or Congregation are remiſſe in Diſcipline, and admit ſuch to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as in his judgement are not fit?</p>
            <p>Was every particular <hi>Corinthian</hi> by communicating guilty of that groſſe profanation of the Sacrament by the Inceſtuous perſon, though in his place he (as it is like ſome few did) laboured to reform it, and mourned for what he could not mend?</p>
            <p>Is not the inſtance of <hi>Achan</hi> for <hi>Relative guilt,</hi> more ſutable to the <hi>Iſraclites</hi> as a Camp then as a Congregation, and as valid againſt fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in an Army as againſt communicating in an Aſſembly where wicked men are admitted?</p>
            <p>May a man under pretence that he <hi>abhorreth Idols, commit ſacriledge;</hi> that is, in Scripture phraſe, rob Churches or Temples of that which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158973:15"/>belongs to them, and convert to private uſe things he never bought or bargain'd for (nor is the propriety of them legally in him, but in others) becauſe he falſly conceiteth (or ſuppoſe truely) that they were at firſt idolatrouſly and ſuperſtitiouſly dedicated to God? Is <hi>gain godlineſſe?</hi> Doth this Reformation ſavour of Conſcionableneſſe or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe? Is there now adays any ſuch ſin as Sacriledge? and what is it?</p>
            <p>Whether the practice of every humane Invention (ſuppoſe thoſe mentioned in theſe Queres prove ſuch) or the practice of every hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inſtitution uſed by the Papiſts (ſuppoſe celebrating and receiving the Lords Supper before dinner, in unleavened bread, bare headed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be ſuch) though accompanied with ſincere hatred and ſolemn renunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Papacie and Popery, be the mark of the Beaſt?</p>
            <p>Can they that receive the mark of the Beaſt, be ſaved without expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite knowledge of it and particular repentance for it?</p>
            <p>Is that the mark of the Beaſt in one Age, that is not in another?</p>
            <p>Was there not both Paſtors and People during all the rage and reign of Antichriſt which did <hi>not receive the mark of the Beaſt,</hi> but their <hi>Fathers name,</hi> and <hi>were Virgins;</hi> and yet did live and die in the practiſe of ſome Traditions uſed by the Papiſts?</p>
            <p>Can it be ſaid either with truth or charity that the reformed Churches or <hi>Waldenſes, Albigenſes,</hi> &amp;c. which were more corrupt then they, did or do <hi>receive the mark of the Beaſt?</hi> and who is he that can or will juſtifie this accuſation?</p>
            <p>Whether, notwithſtanding the apparent differences between the Apoſtolike Churches and ours; the Jewiſh Ceremonies being then ſcarce dead, or at leaſt not buried, their Civil cuſtoms differing from ours, the Church being then but in gathering from amongſt Heathens and Jews, under Heatheniſh and Jewiſh perſecuting Magiſtrates, and endued with extraordinary gifts and offices, (which is not our caſe) the Rites and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eremonies, Practices and Uſages of the Apoſtolike times be unalterably binding to all after-ages?</p>
            <p>Doth Chriſt's faithfulneſſe above <hi>Moſes</hi> conſiſt in a more particular and punctual determination of all externals of Gods Worſhip in the New Teſtament then was given by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Old? Are the times and days of Baptiſm and the Euchariſt as plain as the days and times of Circumciſion and the Paſſeover, the place of meeting, with the utenſils <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the particular way how maintenance ſhould be given to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery as punctually preſcribed in the New Teſtament as in the Old, or the place of, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where in Scripture is that glorious title of The Kingdom of Chriſt, applied to the external policie of the Church; and of all other ways of Church-Government, to the Congregational-way onely and chiefly;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158973:16"/>ſo that no Chriſtians (though never ſo ſyncere and holy) have Chriſt for their King, except they be Church-members, and alſo within the Congregational Covenant; or at leaſt none ſo much as they? And if it be not ſo applied in Scripture, do not they wrong Chriſt his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and people, that preſume ſo to apply it?</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>New England</hi>-men well and warrantably, when their hopes began to languiſh of reducing the erroneous by private means, or by preaching and conference, to hold an Aſſembly of the Churches for diſcovery and confutation of them?</p>
            <p>Had the General Court Civil in <hi>New-England</hi> a lawful power, when <hi>Opinions grew on,</hi> and <hi>experience diſcovered the danger,</hi> to make a Law that Churches ſhould not be ſet up in <hi>N. E.</hi> without the conſent of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Churches there? And hath not the Civil power in <hi>Old England,</hi> from whence theirs is derived, ſeeing the Word of God doth not alter with Climates, the ſame power, when there is the ſame or greater occaſion? And ought not obedience by yeelded here as well as there?</p>
            <p>Would not they that now plead for Liberty of Conſcience and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration in the Kingdom, were they able to root out Presbyterians and their Way, and could Civil Authority enclinable to put forth coercive power againſt it, tell the Magiſtrate that he might (if not, he ought) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it with a ſtrong hand, at leaſt under the notion of being prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to the Civil peace, if it could not otherwiſe be ſuppreſſed?</p>
            <p>Did not the Magiſtrates of <hi>N. E.</hi> when they ſaw that neither preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, conference, nor Aſſembly of the Churches did work the cure of their Diſtractions, but the erroneous went on in their former courſe, not onely to diſturb the Churches, but miſerably alſo to interrupt the Civil Peace, to convent them, and to disfranchiſe ſome, fine others, and baniſh others? Is it true or no, that ſundry ſpeak, and ſome write, that our <hi>N.E.</hi> Brethren would not tolerate a few Presbyterians (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the now-pretended ſmalneſſe of the difference) which were perſecuted for Nonconformity, in any corner of their Countrey; no not ſo much as in that which was next to the <hi>Barbarians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether they which hold Epiſcopal Government to be Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Babyloniſh, to be deſtroyed by fire and ſword; and alſo Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Government to be Antichriſtian, as bad or worſe then Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, be not bound by their principles to root out Presbyterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the reſolute abbettors of it, with fire and ſword, if they can get ability and opportunity for ſuch a deſigne?</p>
            <p>Whether they which have ſolemnly ſworn to <hi>endeavour the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion in Doctrine, Diſcipline, Worſhip and Government,</hi> according to the Word of God and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158973:16"/>and to endeavour the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of the Churches</hi> in the three Kingdoms, and the extirpation of <hi>Popery, Prelacy, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſin,</hi> &amp;c. as all Parliament men, the Aſſembly, and the beſt affected in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom have done, can with good conſcience allow or tolerate Popery, Prelacy, Superſtition, Herefie Schiſm? and why may they not (for any obligation lying upon them by this Covenant) tolerate Popery, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy and Superſtition as well as Hereſie and Schiſm?</p>
            <p>Whether the Parliament can perform thoſe promiſes they have made in the firſt Remonſtrance, and ſince (wherein the Kingdom hath much confided) If <hi>they looſe the golden reins of Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>leave private men or particular Congregations to take up what form of Divine Service they pleaſe,</hi> without requiring <hi>conformity to that Order which the Laws enjoyn ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods Word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have our Brethren expreſſed all their preſent opinions and deſires, or kept ſome for a reſerve? and what may be the reaſon of ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve? Are they fully perſwaded in their own mindes of the truth of all that which they expreſſe themſelves to hold, or onely take them up for the preſent, waiting for further light? May not the Presbyterian-Way, for ought they certainly know (howbeit they at preſent think not ſo) be the Way of God, and moſt agreeable to his Word? And have not expreſſions to this purpoſe proceeded from their Tongues or Pens?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
